The anger in me against corruption
الغضب بداخلي تجاه الفساد
made me to make a big career change
جعلني أخطو خطوة كبيرة في عملي
last year, becoming a full-time practicing lawyer.
في السنة الماضية حيث أصبحت أمارس المحاماة بدوام كامل
My experiences over the last 18 months,
إن تجاربي خلال الثمانية عشر شهرًا التي مضت
as a lawyer, has seeded in me
في عملي في المحاماة
a new entrepreneurial idea,
ألهمني بفكرة ريادية جديدة
which I believe is indeed
التي أؤمن بحق
worth spreading.
أنها تستحق النشر
So, I share it with all of you here today,
لذا سأنشرها اليوم بينكم
though the idea itself is getting crystallized
بالرغم من أن الفكرة بذاتها قيد الصقل
and I'm still writing up the business plan.
وما زلت أكتب الخطة العملية
Of course it helps that fear of public failure
وبالطبع هذا يحد من مخاوف
diminishes as the number of ideas
الفشل العام حيث أن العديد من الأفكار
which have failed increases.
التي فشلت في إزدياد
I've been a huge fan of enterprise and entrepreneurship
كنت وما زلت شديد الإعجاب بمؤسسات الريادة الإجتماعية ومشاريعها
since 1993.
منذ عام 1993
I've explored, experienced,
لقد إستكشفت , و خضت المغامرة
and experimented enterprise
وجربت مشاريع الريادة الإجتماعية
and capitalism to my heart's content.
والرأسمالية من كل قلبي
I built, along with my two brothers,
أنشأت مع أخوين لي
the leading real estate company in my home state, Kerala,
شركة عقارات رائدة في موطني كيرلا
and then worked professionally
وبعدها عملت بصورة محترفة
with two of India's biggest businessmen,
مع إثنين من أكبر رجال أعمال الهند
but in their startup enterprises.
ولكن في بداية مشاريعهم الريادية
In 2003, when I stepped out of the pure play capitalistic sector
و في عام 2003 عندما خرجت من التنافس المحض في القطاع الرأسمالي
to work on so-called social sector issues,
حتى أعمل في قضايا القطاع الإجتماعي
I definitely did not have any grand strategy
كنت بالتأكيد لأ أملك أي إسترتيجية ضخمة
or plan to pursue and find
ولا حتى خطة لمتابعة
for-profit solutions
الحلول الربحية و إيجادها
to addressing pressing public issues.
لمعالجة القضايا العامة الملحة
When life brought about a series
عندما صدمتني الحياة
of death and near-death experiences
بحوادث وفاة و تجارب قرب الموت
within my close circle,
بين المقربين مني
which highlighted the need
أدركت حاجة
for an emergency medical response service in India,
الهند إلى خدمة إستجابة طبية إسعافية
similar to 911 in USA.
مثل "911 الأمريكية"
To address this, I, along with four friends,
ولمعالجة ذلك , قمت أنا مع أربعة من أصدقائي
founded Ambulance Access for All,
بإنشاء "خدمة إسعافية بمتناول الجميع"
to promote life-support ambulance services in India.
لتعزيز الخدمات الإسعافية في الهند لإنقاذ الحياة
For those from the developing world,
وأما لمن هم في الدول النامية
there is nothing, absolutely nothing new in this idea.
فإن هذه الفكرة لا تحمل إطلاقا أي جديد
But as we envisioned it,
ولكن كما نحن تصورناها
we had three key goals:
كانت لدينا 3 أهداف أساسية
Providing world-class life support ambulance service
توفير خدمة إسعافية بطراز عالمي لدعم الحياة
which is fully self-sustainable from its own revenue streams,
التي تكون مستدامة بذاتها وبصفة كلية من خلال إيراداتها
and universally accessible
ويمكن الوصول إليها عالميًا
to anyone in a medical emergency,
لأي شخص في الإسعاف الطبي
irrespective of the capability to pay.
وبصرف النظر عن القدرة على الدفع
The service which grew out of this,
والخدمة التي نتجت عن ذلك
Dial 1298 for Ambulance,
هو الخط الهاتفي للإسعاف 1298
with one ambulance in 2004,
التي بدأت بسيارة إسعاف واحدة في 2004
now has a hundred-plus ambulances in three states,
واليوم لديها مئة سيارة إسعاف في ثلاث ولايات
and has transported over 100,000 patients
ونقلت ما يزيد عن 100 ألف مريض
and victims since inception.
وضحية منذ إنشائها
The service is -- (Applause)
الخدمة هي .. ( تصفيق)
fully self-sustainable from its own revenues,
مستدامة بذاتها وبصفة كلية من إيراداتها الخاصة
without accessing any public funds,
بدون الحصول على تمويل حكومي
and the cross-subsidy model actually works,
و نموذج الإعانة الإضافية قد نجح فعلًا
where the rich pays higher, poor pays lower,
بينما يدفع الأغنياء أكثر , والفقراء أقل
and the accident victim is getting the service free of charge.
ويحصل ضحايا الحوادث على الخدمة مجانا
The service responded effectively
وأصبحت الخدمة فعالة
and efficiently,
وبكفاءه في
during the unfortunate
الأحداث المؤسفة
26/11 Mumbai terror attacks.
للهجمات الإرهابية في مومباي 26/11
And as you can see from the visuals,
وكما ترون من خلال الشاشة
the service was responding and rescuing
كانت الخدمة تتفاعل و تنقذ
victims from the incident locations
الضحايا من موقع الحادثة
even before the police could cordon off
حتى قبل أن تطوق الشرطة
the incident locations
موقع الحادثة
and formally confirm it as a terror strike.
وقبل تأكيدهم لها بأنها ضربة إرهابية
We ended up being the first medical response team
كنا نحن أول فريق طبي يستجيب
in every incident location
في كل مواقع الحادثة
and transported 125 victims,
ونقلنا 125 ضحية
saving life.
منقذين بذلك حياتهم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
In tribute and remembrance
وتقديرًا للضحايا وفي ذكرى
of 26/11 attacks
هجمات 26/11
over the last one year,
عملنا في السنة الماضية
we have actually helped a Pakistani NGO,
على مساعدة منظمة غير حكومية بكستانية
Aman Foundation,
تسمى "مؤسسة آمان"
to set up a self-sustainable life support ambulance service
لإنشاء خدمة إسعافية مستدامة بذاتها لدعم الحياة
in Karachi, facilitated by Acumen Fund.
في مدينة كراتشي , بدعم من صندوق "أكيومن"
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's a small message from us,
إنها رسالة قصيرة منا
in our own small way
بطريقتنا الصغيرة
to the enemies of humanity,
لأعداء الإنسانية
of Islam, of South Asia,
واعداء الإسلام , وأعداء جنوب آسيا
of India, and of Pakistan,
واعداء الهند و بكستان
that humanity will continue to bloom,
أن الإنسانية سوف تبقى على إزدهارها
irrespective of such dastardly attacks.
بغض النظر عن الهجمات المدمرة
Since then I've also co-founded two other social enterprises.
وقمت أيضًا بالمشاركة في إنشاء مشروعين للريادة الإجتماعية
One is Education Access for All,
أحدهما هو "الحصول على التعليم للجميع"
setting up schools in small-town India.
بإنشاء مدارس في المدن الصغيرة في الهند
And the other is Moksha-Yug Access,
والاخر هو "الحصول على الموكشا (الحرية)"
which is integrating rural supply chain
وهي سلسلة حلول لسد حاجة القروي
on the foundations of self-help group-based microfinance.
بتكوين مجموعة لمساعدة ذاتها معتمدة على تمويل المشاريع الصغيرة
I guess we seem to be doing at least a few things right.
أظن بأننا نقوم بالصحيح في بعض الأشياء
Because diligent investors and venture funds
وذلك لأن المستثمرين الكادين , و الصناديق الإستثمارية
have committed over 7.5 million dollars in funding.
أودعت ما يزيد عن 7.5 مليون دولار في التمويل
With the significance being these funds have come in
مع أهمية ذكر أن تلك التمويلات دخلت
as a QT capital, not as grant or as philanthropy.
كرؤوس أموال بقيمة سوقية , وليس كمنحة , أو عمل خيري
Now I come back to the idea of the new social enterprise
أعود الآن إلى فكرة المشروع الريادي الإجتماعي الجديد
that I'm exploring.
التي أستكشفها
Corruption, bribes, and lack of transparency.
الفساد , و الرشاوي , و نقص الشفافية
You may be surprised to know
قد تتفاجئون عندما تعلمون
that eight speakers yesterday
أن 8 متحدثين أمس
actually mentioned these terms in their talks.
ذكروا هذه المصطلحات خلال حديثهم
Bribes and corruption have both a demand and a supply side,
لدى كلا الرشاوي والفساد جانبين للطلب والعرض
with the supply side being mostly of
و بكون جانب العرض
greedy corporate unethical businesses
أكثر من الشركات التجارية الجشعة واللأخلاقية
and hapless common man.
وشخص منحوس من عامة الناس
And the demand side being mostly politicians,
وبكون جانب الطلب أكثر من السياسيين
bureaucrats and those who have discretionary power
والبيروقراطين و الذين لديهم سلطة تقديرية
vested with them.
مخولة لهم
According to World Bank estimate,
وطبقًا لتقديرات البنك الدولي
one trillion dollars is paid in bribes
فإن ترليون دولار تدفع كرشاوي
every year, worsening the condition
كل عام مما يزيد من سوء الوضع
of the already worse off.
الذي هو سيء الآن
Yet, if you analyze the common man,
ولكن إذا حللتم نفسيًا الشخص المنحوس من عامة الناس
he or she does not wake up every day and say,
فهو أو هي لا يستيقظون كل يوم ويقولوا
"Hmm, let me see who I can pay a bribe to today."
هممم دعنى أفكر من أدفع له الرشوة اليوم
or, "Let me see who I can corrupt today."
او دعنى أفكر كيف أفسد أي شيء اليوم
Often it is the constraining or the back-to-the-wall situation
غالبًا إنه الوضع الذي يقيد يد الجميع
that the hapless common man finds himself or herself in
والذي يجعل الشخص المنحوس من عامة الناس في موقف
that leads him to pay a bribe.
يجعله يدفع الرشوة
In the modern day world, where time is premium
وفي عالمنا الحديث اليوم , حيث للوقت اهميته
and battle for subsistence is unimaginably tough,
والمعركة من أجل البقاء يصعب تخيلها
the hapless common man
فإن الشخص المنحوس من عامة الناس
simply gives in and pays the bribe just to get on with life.
يعطي الرشوة ويقبلها حتى تسير الحياة
Now, let me ask you another question.
والآن إسمحوا لي بطرح سؤال آخر
Imagine you are being asked to pay a bribe
تخيل أن يطلب منك دفع رشوة
in your day-to-day life to get something done.
في حياتك اليومية لإنجاز شيء ما
What do you do? Of course you can call the police.
ماذا تفعل؟ بالطبع تستطيع الإتصال بالشرطة
But what is the use if the police department is in itself steeped in corruption?
ولكن ماذا ستفعل إن كان قسم الشرطة في حد ذاته فاسد ؟
Most definitely you don't want to pay the bribe.
في أغلب الأحوال لن ترغب في دفع الرشوة
But you also don't have the time, resources,
ولكن في نفس الوقت ليس لديك الوقت , ولا المصادر
expertise or wherewithal to fight this.
ولا الخبرة والمال الكافي لمكافحة ذلك
Unfortunately, many of us in this room
للأسف , العديد منا في هذه الغرفة
are supporters of capitalist policies and market forces.
داعمين للأنظمة الرأسمالية وقوى السوق
Yet the market forces around the world
ولكن قوى السوق حول العالم
have not yet thrown up a service where you can call in,
لم تقم أي خدمة تستطيع بها الإتصال
pay a fee, and fight the demand for a bribe.
ودفع رسوم , و مكافحة الحاجة إلى رشوة
Like a bribe buster service,
مثل خدمة القبض على المرتشين
or 1-800-Fight-Bribes,
أو 1-800- للقبض على المرتشين
or www.stopbribes.org or
او موقع www.stopbribes.org
www.preventcorruption.org.
او موقع www.preventcorruption.org
Such a service simply do not exist.
مثل هذه الخدمة بكل بساطة غير موجودة
One image that has haunted me
ظلت صورة واحدة عالقة في ذهني
from my early business days
من أيام عملي السابق
is of a grandmother, 70 plus years, being harassed
وهي صورة جدة في ال70 من عمرها يتحرش بها
by the bureaucrats in the town planning office.
البيروقراطيين في مكتب التخطيط في المدينة
All she needed was permission to build three steps
كل ما كانت تحتاجه السماح لها ببناء ثلاث أدراج
to her house, from ground level,
أمام بيتها من مستوى سطح الأرض
making it easier for her to enter and exit her house.
مما يسهل عليها دخول بيتها والخروج منه
Yet the officer in charge would not simply give her the permit
ولكن الموظف المسؤول رفض إعطائها الإذن بكل سهولة
for want of a bribe.
لأنه يريد رشوة !
Even though it pricked my conscience then,
على الرغم من أن ضميري كان يؤنبني
I could not, or rather I did not
إلا أنني لم أكن أستطيع فعل شيء
tend to her or assist her,
أو لأصدق القول لم أرد مساعدتها
because I was busy building my real estate company.
لأني كنت مشغول ببناء شركتي للعقارات
I don't want to be haunted by such images any more.
لا أريد لمثل تلك الصور بملاحقتي بعد الآن
A group of us have been working on a pilot basis
عملت مجموعة منا على أسس تجريبية
to address individual instances of demands
في معالجة حالات فردية لطلبات
for bribes for common services or entitlement.
رشاوي من الخدمات العامة , أو المستحقة
And in all 42 cases where we have pushed back such demands
وفي كل الحالات الـ 42 أزحنا مثل هذه المطالب
using existing and legitimate tools
بإستخدام طرق تشريعية و موجودة
like the Right to Information Act,
مثل حق قانون الحصول على معلومات
video, audio, or peer pressure,
وبتسجيل مقاطع فيديو , أو صوتيات , أو ضغط على الأقران
we have successfully obtained whatever our clients
حققنا فعلا كل ما يريده عملائنا
set out to achieve without actually paying a bribe.
بدون دفع أي رشوة
And with the cost of these tools being substantially lower
وبكون هذه الأدوات أقل تكلفة بصورة ملحوظة
than the bribe demanded.
من مطالب الرشوة
I believe that these tools that worked in these 42 pilot cases
أؤمن بأن هذه الأدوات التي عملنا بها في الـ42 حالة التجربيية
can be consolidated in standard processes
يمكن أن تكون موحدة في العمليات المعيارية
in a BPO kind of environment,
في بيئة تعتمد تعهيد الخدمات الإجرائية
and made available on web, call-center
وتوفير موقع , ومركز إتصالات
and franchise physical offices,
ومكاتب إمتياز فعلية
for a fee, to serve anyone confronted with a demand for a bribe.
مقابل رسم لمساعدة أي شخص واجه طلب لرشوة
The target market is as tempting as it can get.
والسوق المستهدف مغري بكثرة ذلك
It can be worth up to one trillion dollars,
وقد تصل إلى تريليون دولار
being paid in bribes every year,
تدفع في الرشاوي كل عام
or equal to India's GDP.
أو قد تساوي الناتج المحلي الإجمالي للهند
And it is an absolutely virgin market.
وهو بالتأكيد سوقٌ ناشيء
I propose to explore this idea further,
أقترح بإستكشاف أوسع لهذه الفكرة
to examine the potential of creating
لدراسة فرص إيجاد
a for-profit, fee-based BPO
خدمات ربحية , معتمدة على رسم تعهيد الخدمات الإجرائية
kind of service to stop bribes
لإيقاف الرشاوي
and prevent corruption.
ومنع الفساد
I do realize that the fight for justice
أدرك بأن الكفاح للعدل
against corruption is never easy.
أمام الفسد ليس سهلًا
It never has been and it never will be.
لم تكن سهلة , ولن تكون كذلك
In my last 18 months as a lawyer,
في الـ18 شهر التي مضت كمحامي
battling small- and large-scale corruption,
أحارب بها الفساد بكل مقاييسه صغيرا كان أم كبيرا
including the one perpetrated by India's biggest corporate scamster.
ومن ضمنها تلك التي إرتكبتها إحدى أكبر شركات الهند إحتيالًا
Through his charities
من خلال جمعياتهم الخيرية
I have had three police cases filed against me
وقد رفعت علي 3 قضايا من الشرطة
alleging trespass, impersonation and intimidation.
بإدعاء التعدي على ممتلكات الغير , وانتحال الشخصية , والترهيب
The battle against corruption
محاربة الفساد
exacts a toll on ourselves,
يجلب مصائب لأنفسنا
our families, our friends, and even our kids.
وأسرنا , و أصدقائنا , أو حتى أبنائنا
Yet I believe the price we pay is well worth holding on
ومع ذلك فإني أؤمن بأن الثمن الذي ندفعه يستحق التمسك
to our dignity and making the world a fairer place.
بكرامتنا , وبجعل العالم مكانًا أكثر عدالة
What gives us the courage?
ما الذي يعطينا الشجاعة؟
As my close friend replied, when told
وكما رد صديقي ذات مرة عندما سئل ذلك
during the seeding days of the ambulance project
في الأيام الأولى لمشروع الإسعاف
that it is an impossible task
قالوا بأن هذه مهمة مستحيلة
and the founders are insane to chalk up their blue-chip jobs,
والمؤسسين حتما مجانين لتركهم أعمالهم الناجحة
I quote: "Of course we cannot fail in this,
وأقتبس هنا عنه "بالطبع لا نستطيع الفشل في ذلك
at least in our own minds.
على الأقل في عقلنا
For we are insane people,
بما أننا أشخاص مجانين
trying to do an impossible task.
نحاول تنفيذ مهمة مستحيلة
And an insane person does not know what an impossible task is." Thank you.
والشخص المجنون لا يعلم ماهية المستحيل في المهمة " شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Chris Anderson: Shaffi, that is a really exciting business idea.
كريس اندرسون : شافي ، إنها حقا فكرة تجارية مثيرة للإهتمام
Shaffi Mather: I just have to get through the initial days where I don't get eliminated.
شافي ماثر: علي فقط أن أتخطى الأيام الأولى حتى لا يتم إستبعادي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
CA: What's on your mind?
كريس: ماذا يدور في خلدك؟
I mean, give us a sense of the numbers here --
أعني أعطنا لمحة عن هذه الأرقام هنا --
a typical bribe and a typical fee. I mean, what's in your head?
مثال لرشوة ومثال لغرامة. أعني، مالذي يدور بخلدك؟
SM: So let me ... Let me give you an example.
شافي: إذاً دعني...لأعطيكم مثالاً.
Somebody who had applied for the passport.
شخص ما قدم طلباً لإستصدار جواز سفر
The officer was just sitting on it
وكان الضابط يتلكأ عليه
and was demanding around 3,000 rupees in bribes.
ويطالب بحوالي 3000 آلالاف روبية كرشوة.
And he did not want to pay.
وهو لا يريد أن يدفع الرشوة
So we actually used the Right to Information Act,
لذا فنحن أستخدمنا قانون الحق في الحصول على المعلومات،
which is equal to the Freedom of Information Act in the United States,
الذي هو مكافئ لقانون حق الحصول على معلومات في الولايات المتحدة،
and pushed back the officers in this particular case.
وقمنا بإيقاف الضابط في هذه الحالة تحديداً.
And in all these 42 cases,
وفي كل هذه ال 42 حالة،
when we kept pushing them back,
عندما كنا نقوم بالضغط عليهم،
there was three kinds of reaction.
كانت هناك ثلاث ردود أفعال.
A set of people actually say,
يقول مجموعة من الناس،
"Oh, let me just grant it to them, and run away from it."
"أوه، دعني فقط أدفع لهم الرشوة ، وأنأى بنفسي منهم."
Some people actually come back and say,
بعض الناس جاءوا في الواقع وقالوا،
"Oh, you want to screw me. Let me show you what I can do."
"أوه، تريدون الإيقاع بي. لأريكم مالذي أستطيع فعله."
And he will push us back.
وقام بدفعنا إلى الخلف.
So you take the next step, or use the next tool available
فتقوم أنت بأخذ الخطوة التالية، أو تستخدم الأداة التالية المتوفرة
in what we are putting together,
فيما نضعه سوياً،
and then he relents.
ثم نجده قد قام بتليين موقفه
By the third time, in all 42 cases, we have achieved success.
ببلوغ المرحلة الثالثة في كل ال 42 حالة، كنا قد حققنا النجاح.
CA: But if it's a 3,000-rupee, 70-dollar bribe,
كريس: لكن إذا كانت هي رشوة ب 3000 ، يعني 70 دولاراً،
what fee would you have to charge,
كم المبلغ الذي ينبغي أن يدفعه،
and can you actually make the business work?
ويمكنك تحقيق نجاح العمل؟
SM: Well, actually the cost that we incurred
شافي: حسناً، في الواقع التكلفة التي نتكبدها
was less than 200 rupees.
كانت أقل من 200 روبية.
So, it actually works.
لذا، فهي تعمل في الواقع.
CA: That's a high gross margin business. I like it.
كريس: إنه لهامش ربحي مرتفع. أنا أحب ذلك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
SM: I actually did not want to answer this on the TED stage.
شافي: في الواقع، لم أرد أن أبوح بهذا على خشبة مسرح تيد.
CA: OK, so these are provisional numbers, no pricing guarantee.
كريس: حسناً، إذاً فهذه أرقام مقترحة، لا توجد ضمانات للتسعيرة
If you can pull this off, you will be a global hero.
إذا أستطعت الإستمرار والنجاح في هذا فأنت بطل عالمي.
I mean, this could be huge.
أعني، قد يصبح هذا شيئاً ضخماً.
Thank you so much for sharing this idea at TED.
شكراً جزيلاً لك على تقاسم هذه الفكرة عبر تيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)